<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title> - personal</title>
      <link>https://www.bytekeeper.org</link>
      <description></description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://www.bytekeeper.org/tags/personal/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>A son was born</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://www.bytekeeper.org/2020-05-16/</link>
          <guid>https://www.bytekeeper.org/2020-05-16/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://www.bytekeeper.org/2020-05-16/">&lt;p&gt;This was meant to be a tech related blog, mostly for Broodwar AI related stuff and private projects. Since private projects are included, I guess one could call my son a private project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Screaming into the light, he was born in late February. His name is Benjamin, which I am certain means horse-dung in some weird language. I do not care, go away! And due to Corona, we have been left alone for most of the time since then.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My last blog entry was in January, and up until now I really did not have the energy to write a new article. But since most of my free time is now reserved for serving the little demon, I&#x27;ll just write about what
I know best now: My spawn. Prepare for many picture which may or may not include my son (hint: nope, no pix from him - maybe in a later post).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all babies, he is cute (actually I believe mostly parents find most babies cute, for my part they look like french baguettes mostly...). If you remember Tamagochi, it is really its human form.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucky for me, we have a spare room - otherwise working would be very hard due to missing shut-eye. Which means shift 1 is work, shift 2 is work, shift 3 is sleep. And things like &lt;em&gt;this&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; mostly eat into shift 3.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little human goes through a lot of development phases. There is the cute phase...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;margin: 0; line-height: 1em; font-size: 0.9em&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;Cute-Baby.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; alt=&quot;Not mine&quot;&#x2F;&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Not mine&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is the crying phase...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;margin: 0; line-height: 1em; font-size: 0.9em&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;crying_baby.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; alt=&quot;Still not mine&quot;&#x2F;&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Nope, still not mine&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is the default happy phase&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;margin: 0; line-height: 1em; font-size: 0.9em&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;screaming-yoda.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; alt=&quot;Really, what the&quot;&#x2F;&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Definitely not mine &lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, the last one might be slightly exaggerated. And it is not the default. At least for my son, most of the time he is pretty happy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are supposed to react to the baby&#x27;s needs. Ignore that at your own peril (eardrums). Really, a lot of time I look at my son and this is what I see:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;margin: 0; line-height: 1em; font-size: 0.9em&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;mischievous-baby.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; alt=&quot;Are the all able to look like thatReally, what the?&quot;&#x2F;&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Same smirk, but not mine&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the general baby package works like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You receive it&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It comes un-boxed, without manual - W.T.H.?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It must already be defect, or is it supposed to behave this way&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your midwife (its common to have one here) tells you a lot of good info, and a lot of mumbo-jumbo.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She tells you what homeopathy &quot;stuff&quot; (I refuse to say medicine here) you can give you baby - that is ok, since placebo also works for babies. (Btw did you know, there is also a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Nocebo&quot;&gt;nocebo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; effect? Cool!)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She tells you to see an osteopath (that is so much dumbfuckery). Uuuuhhhh magic energy waves uuuuhh&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You start to get a grip on it... or do you?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thing is, the first few weeks you could care less. Your baby can see like 30cm (about 12in you strange people who stopped in time). It can&#x27;t really focus or look at you.
After that it actually can focus you, which is good - it can now target practice with its sound-wave gun &lt;em&gt;while looking at you&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it starts to smile at you. First for short periods of time, then more. It might also randomly switch from crying, screaming, and laughing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#x27;re currently within the Stan phase. What that is?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.bytekeeper.org&#x2F;2020-05-16&#x2F;stan.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Stan&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, I will conclude today&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;rant&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
